Guide to the Barbara Gittings and Kay Tobin Lahusen collection,1965-2007.
Gittings, Barbara and Kay Tobin Lahusen collection,1965-2007.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Barbara Gittings and Kay Tobin Lahusen collection, 1965-2007.
7645
Barbara Gittings
0.4 cubic feet
Publications, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
News clippings featuring Gittings over her years of lesbian and gay rights activism, 1965-2007, including photocopies of photographs of Gittings in demonstrations in front of Independence Hall on July 4, 1966 and July 4, 1969 and in front of the White House in October 1965, a clipping about Gittings' 1969 visit to speak at Cornell University, and obituaries and information about her memorial service. Also, brochures, position statements, and flyers from gay rights events and organizations, including election materials from Franklin Kameny's congressional run in 1971, and 1982 news clippings about efforts to establish a gay scholarship and gay book fund at Cornell.
Also, DVD "Gay Pioneers" and video "Out of the Past" (a documentary about the gay rights movement)
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Gittings and Lahusen played important roles in the gay liberation movement emerging in the 1950s. Gittings helped organize the New York City chapter of the Daughters of Bilitis in 1958. Lahusen joined the New York City Daughters of Bilitis in 1961, and the two met there. From 1963-66, Gittings served as editor of DOB's periodical publication, THE LADDER, and Lahusen worked on it with her. Lahusen co-authored THE GAY CRUSADERS in 1972. Gittings was active in the campaign that led to the American Psychiatric Association dropping its categorization of homosexuality as a mental illness in 1973. Gittings was also active in the American Library Association for 16 years. Though not a librarian, she was an avid book lover, and joined ALA's Task Force on Gay Liberation as soon as she found out about it in 1970. Gittings and Lahusen remained active in the gay civil rights movement and remained partners until Gittings' death on Febrary 18, 2007.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
DVD "Gay Pioneers" and video "Out of the Past" (a documentary about the gay rights movement), news clippings featuring Gittings, including clippings about the video "Out of the Past," and photocopies of photographs of Gittings in gay rights demonstrations in front of Independence Hall on July 4, 1966 and July 4, 1969, and in front of the White House in October 1965. Also, obituaries and information about Gittings' memorial service; brochures, position statements, flyers and clippings from gay rights events and organizations and on various gay rights subjects, including election materials from Franklin Kameny's congressional run in 1971; and a 1969 clipping about Gittings' visit to speak at Cornell University and 1982 news clippings about efforts to establish a gay scholarship and gay book funds at Cornell.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Gittings, Barbara,1932-; Gittings, Barbara, 1932-; Lahusen, Kay Tobin.
Subjects:
Gay liberation movement--United States.; Gays--Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Library fund raising.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Collecting program: Human Sexuality Collection.
Original of the July 4, 1969 photograph taken by Nancy Tucker is at the Lesbian Herstory Archives in Brooklyn, NY.
SERIES LIST
Series I. About Gittings
Series II. Subject Files
Series III. Organizational Files
Series IV. Clippings and Ephemera
Series V. Videos
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. About Gittings
  - Obituaries and memorial service, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resume (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Speech: 4th annual Christopher Street Liberation Day March, New York City, 24-Jun-73 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gittings at Cornell, Oct-69 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 11 items donated in 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Photocopies of photographs of Gittings in gay rights demonstrations in front of Independence Hall on July 4, 1966 and July 4, 1969, and in front of the White House in October 1965. News clippings about the video "Out of the Past," a documentary about the gay rights movement, and 1982 news clippings about efforts to establish a gay scholarship and gay book funds at Cornell University.
  - Clippings on Gittings, 1970-2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series II. Subject Files
  - Child custody: Judd Marmor, M.D., letter to Bruce Voeller, 3-May-73 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Decriminalizing Homosexuality (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Police and Entrapment (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Discrimination Policies, 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Military, Ca. 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Psychology, clippings and statements, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Religion (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - College and University Issues
    - Flyers for Campus Events (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Course Syllabi and Campus Issues (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Teaching and Children's Books (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Book Issues
    - Lesbian Book, call for submissions, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - J. Michael McConnell, U of Minnesota librarian job discrimination case, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Library Issues (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reminder Day, Philadelphia, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Barney Frank for Massachusetts State Representative, [1972] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kameny for Congress, Ca. 1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series III. Organizational Files
  - American Civil Liberties Union, Ca. 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - American Library Association Task Force on Gay Liberation and Gay Task Force, Ca. 1970-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Daughters of Bilitis, Ca. 1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Eastern Regional Homophile Conference, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Gay Activists Alliance, Philadelphia and New York City (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gay Liberation of Minnesota: "Love and Let Love" brochure, Ca. 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Homophile Action League (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Homophile Action League, Philadelphia (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Janus Society (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mattachine Society of Washington, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mattachine, New York City (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Organization for Women: 1971 resolution on lesbian rights and lesbian custody issues and 1975 Lesbian Caucus Resolution, Fall 1971, October 26, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Queens Liberation Front, cross dressers, New York City, Ca. 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Student Homophile League, including "Statement on the Lesbian", Ca. 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Student Homophile League, Columbia University (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series IV. Clippings and Ephemera
  - Film showings and advertisements (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Brochures, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Gay Rights Ephemera, miscellaneous, 1967-1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, annotated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Notes and clippings re: Oliva (1951) and movie 'The Pit of Loneliness' (1954) with photo of NGTF Staff (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series V. Videos
  - Gay Pioneers, 515 (Box 2)
  - Out of the Past, 442 (Box 2)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
The following publications have been separated from collection 7645 and cataloged as individual titles in the Human Sexuality Collection.
Feb. 15, 1974 Commonweal offprint,
May 1973 Connexion (United Methodist Board of Higher Education and Ministry)
Gay Insurgent - nos. 6-7
1972-1973 Gay People and Mental Health - v.1
1969-1971 Homphophile Action League. Newsletter
1958-1966 The Ladder - various issues
1968 Daughters of Bilitis, Philadelphia Chapter. Newsletter - v.1: no.8-11